Parking, Unlimited

I could have taken that three hundred dollars and gone to school for a year, by washing dishes two hours a night. I had worked for that money, too; shocking wheat for twelve hours a day in the August sun is no vacation. But Slim Coleman convinced me that we could run that three hundred into enough to take us both for four years.

I hadn’t even had time to get a haircut—and I did want a haircut; now it was pretty shaggy.

But Slim, diplomat that he is, didn’t even seem to notice my hair. “I’ve got a real deal,” he said, and his deep eyes were shining with enthusiasm. “Have you got any money?”

“Some,” I said cautiously.

“It takes three hundred. Have you got that much?”

I had intended to say no, but Slim has a way of fixing his deep, somber eyes on you that gives ineffable dignity even to a touch. “Okay,” I said hopelessly. “What’s the bite?”

“Well, you see, it’s like this.” We went into a drug store and ordered cokes, and Slim characteristically insisted on paying for them when he probably couldn’t have bought a package of cigarettes. I let him pay, too. I had three hundred and one dollars, and I had no intention of parting with a nickel of it—except a dollar for a haircut.

“I was using the brain-finder and I ran across the owner of this unused garage in the Loop. His name is Richard LaBombard and he’s got a lot of parking lots through the Loop, and you know what he’s doing?”

I saw the waitress stare at me. I swallowed and tried to listen to Slim. “No.”

Slim was staring at the waitress. “He loads them up with used cars every day so those who are hunting a parking place can’t get in,” he said absently. “You know what he wants?”

“Well, no.” I never could figure those things, but Slim could see the angles a mile away. He was always good at that.

“He’s made an application for a permit to build a parking ramp that will cover a solid block down in the middle of the Loop. Now, if he can build a place to park eight or ten thousand cars, naturally that one spot is going to be the best business spot in the city. And Richard LaBombard holds leases or options on half the store space around that block. He stands to make millions.”

“Where does my three hundred come in?”

Slim ignored the acidulousness in my voice. “Well, as I say, I followed him with the brain-finder and found him holding hands with the mayor’s wife at a skating rink—and the next day I—ah—persuaded him to give me an option to lease this building on the edge of the Loop.”

“You mean you blackmailed him.”

“That’s a harsh word. I prefer ‘persuaded’ myself. After all, he wouldn’t want something like that to come up just when he’s finagling for that permit, would he? Anyway, I paid five dollars for the option.”

“That’s unusual. You’ve got some of your own money in this deal.”

Like a gentleman, Slim ignored that thrust. “Tomorrow is the first. I’ve got to raise two hundred and fifty for a month’s rent. We’ll need fifty more for deposits on light, heat, and power. We’ll make a million within a month. We split fifty-fifty.”

“How do you make the million?”

Slim looked around. Nobody was near; he leaned close and whispered. “This is the invention of the century. We can solve the parking problem of the entire city. You know how it is—you can’t even get into a parking lot after ten a.m. Lots of businesses are threatening to put branches out in the suburbs.”

“Yes?”

“The parking problem must be solved if the city is to survive,” Slim said dramatically.

“Okay, but how can you make any more out of an old building than anybody else?”

He whispered again. “I can create a magnetic field that will slow electrons down to almost zero velocity. A car will shrink to about four inches long.” He stared at me intently. “Do you see what that will mean?”

I sighed. “I’m afraid I do. If it works, you can pack a million cars in a space that ordinarily would hold about a thousand.” I tried to stop my enthusiasm, but it was too late. The idea was taking hold. “And that garage is right across the street from Newton’s, the biggest department store in the city.”

“The parking problem was intensified last week when they abolished parking on the street so the afternoon traffic could get through. Boy, this is the spot for us!” Slim said.

“Will it take all of three hundred dollars?” I asked Slim.

He nodded gravely, “Every cent. And then it will be a shoestring.”

“Wouldn’t two hundred and ninety-nine be enough?”

“No,” said Slim. He looked back at me. He had always been that way; he never compromised with my money.

I shuddered when I saw my hair in the mirror as we left. But, I knew I’d better keep the dollar for cigarettes. …

We paid the first month’s rent; I put up the deposits, and Slim brought a bunch of wire and stuff from his basement, and we worked till one o’clock winding gadgets and building a regular stall to run a car into. This garage had a ramp going to the basement floor, and we decided to use that floor. Also, there was an old freight elevator up to the second and third floors, and we could park a few on the main floor and send a few upstairs when we had time, because of course we didn’t want the secret to get out.

Slim tried the squeezer-upper when he got it finished. He set a couple of old sawhorses inside and, turned on the juice. It was uncanny to see those things shrink. You could even hear the legs scrape on the concrete floor as they pulled together. In just about three seconds the sawhorses were an inch high. Then Slim reversed the current and they expanded to normal size again. All this in about one breath.

“But look,” I said, suddenly stricken with a horrible thought. “What if you don’t get a car back exactly the size it was at first? Then new tires wouldn’t fit, new parts wouldn’t fit—oh, my goodness!” I was abruptly overwhelmed with the enormity of such damage.

“That’s all taken care of,” he assured me. “The electrons in any given object seem to have a tendency to resume their former orbits if they get a chance. In other words, if I expand a car to almost its normal size and then cut off the power, the electrons will sort of coast into their original orbits and the car will resume its exact former size. Sort of a quantum jump, I suppose.”

I breathed a deep sigh of relief.

“Of course, if you go too far, you’ll have an oversize car, but you could reduce it again,” said Slim. “Now in the morning we’ll hang out a parking sign and let them drive onto the main floor. You run the cars into the basement, and we’ll have this thing down under the ramp, out of sight.” Slim’s deep eyes were glowing. “We’ll make a million,” he said, rubbing his hands.

Well, by the end of the next day it began to look as if we had, indeed, solved the most urgent problem of modern civilization—the parking problem. We had a sign out that said, Parking All Day 50c—No one Turned Away, and by the end of the day we had taken in nearly five hundred dollars.

But it was a mankiller. I handed out claim checks and drove cars to the basement. Slim reduced them and hauled them across the room to a lineup. That was funny—seeing a car shrink to three or four inches long. It was an irresistible impulse to pick it up, but when you tried, you changed your mind. The cars were practically as heavy in their small size as in their big size, and that made it something of a problem to get them moved around.

We had borrowed a toe-and-heel, a sort of crowbar with rollers on it, and with the reduced friction from the extremely small tires of the cars, it wasn’t too hard to move them, but it was still a mankiller to move a thousand in one day, and move each twice. We took turns at the reducer. I could handle them best by catching them under the front axle, but we decided to make them six inches long so it would be easier. The metal in its smaller size seemed as tough as it had been normally, but the parts were pretty small to get hold of with anything strong enough to handle them.

Slim solved this problem the second day when he put a long piece of gas-pipe on the heel-and-toe and shrank it considerably. The second day, too, we had two men working upstairs. The third day we had a gadget made so that we could roll a car’s front wheel on it and then pull the car anywhere. That was when we began to get our breath. The other way had been tough. I don’t know how Slim stood it at all; if I hadn’t worked in the wheat-fields all summer I would have fallen from exhaustion.

We had two of those gadgets made and then we tilted the reducing stall a little. We’d block the wheels with a two-by-four after we had a car inside, then reduce it, take out the block, let the car roll onto the gadget and haul it away. We arranged them on the concrete floor in rows about four feet apart. When somebody came back to get their car out we had to pinch-bar the car back up on the gadget and wheel it to the stall.

The second week we had two stalls, one reducing and one expanding, and Slim was talking of having a new sloping floor put in to help in handling. By that time we were handling two thousand cars a day; you can do your own arithmetic.

On the last day of the month, LaBombard came in to collect his next month’s rent. He was all eyes and he said he didn’t see how we could do it. “You took in twenty-two hundred cars yesterday and this building won’t hold over six hundred,” he said, his eyes darting all around. “You must have a fast turnover.”

Slim kidded him. “We put ’em on the roof,” he said, and paid him and pushed him out. I didn’t like the look in that man’s eyes as he left.

“Well,” said Slim exuberantly to me, “we’re sitting on thirty thousand dollars. Think you can get through college on that?”

“I hope I can take time off to get a haircut,” I said fervently. It was embarrassing to have people look at me and suddenly snicker and turn away to hide their faces. The trouble was, we didn’t dare turn the reducing over to anybody else, and so we both worked like robots.

By the beginning of the second month we had a moving ramp. The boys upstairs put the car on the ramp, the car came downstairs and went through the reducer, came out on the other side and onto a platform. We had a tow-truck that just backed up, reached down a steel platform under the front axle, and walked away. It was funny to see that two-ton truck hauling a toy car across the floor.

Yes, we had a deal. Late at night, after we’d closed up and had time for some coffee, Slim would talk about how we were going to build a chain of parking ramps across the country.

“We’ll make billions,” he said, his deep eyes shining with a faraway fanaticism that only Slim Coleman can exhibit, “and we’ll be known as the saviors of civilization. We’ll call ourselves Parking Unlimited.”

Then one night the building inspector came. We were just resting for a moment, with no cars in sight, when we looked around and there he stood. It startled us, because absolutely no one was allowed in the basement.

“What do you want?” Slim asked, and just then a car appeared on the ramp, coming down to the reducer.

“I’m the building inspector. I’m checking on the weight you’re putting in this building. It’s an old building, you know.” And all the time his eyes were darting everywhere.

“Did LaBombard send you?” asked Slim. The car was halfway down.

“Well, not exactly; we’re interested in this from the safety angle.”

A second car’s nose showed around the curve. I began to sweat.

“Okay,” said Slim. “Look us over. We do the parking upstairs.”

“What do you do down here?” The inspector stared at the reducing stall.

“That’s a newfangled washing apparatus.”

“What are all these toy cars on the floor down here?”

I practically swallowed my tongue. I had known that was coming.

But Slim said casually, “Oh, we’re making Christmas presents in our spare time.” The first car was about to enter the reducing stall.

The inspector stared at the two thousand cars on the basement floor. “They look plenty real.”

I held my breath. If he should ever try to pick up one of those cars, it would be all over for us. I could just imagine what two thousand owners would say if they should find out their cars had been reduced to six inches. People are not too broad-minded about such things.

But Slim had him by the elbow. With the savage shake of his head at me and the reducing stall, he said, “I’ll take you up and show you around.” They rode the ramp upstairs.

Right then I wanted to lie down and pass out with sheer relief, but the cars were beginning to pile up. I worked like a horse for half an hour, doing double duty. Then Slim came back with a haunting sadness in his eyes, and a faraway look that was not encouraging.

“We’ve got to get out of here,” he said. “He knows too much. Too many parking-lot people are putting on the heat.”

“You mean he knows how we are packing them in?”

“No, but he knows that we are taking in as many as three thousand cars a day, while half the parking lots in town are begging for customers.”

I sighed. “When are we leaving?”

Slim’s eyes were looking far away. “At the end of the week,” he said. “We’ve got enough money in the bank to pay all our bills. We’ve got a couple thousand in the safe, and we’ll take in three or four more. Tomorrow’s Friday. The next day will be Saturday and we should handle four thousand cars. We blow Saturday night. We’ll go to the coast.”

“Will I have time to get a haircut?” I asked hopefully.

“No. Get your hair cut in L.A.” He went on dreamily, “We should have five thousand. We can start up again, and this time we’ll start off right, so we can run indefinitely without anybody catching on. We’ve got some capital to work with now.”

Friday was a good day. Slim only chuckled when I told him there was a man sitting across the street with a pad of paper and a pencil, tallying the cars that came in and those that went out.

“We’re good for tomorrow,” said Slim, “then they can have it. I’ve got plane reservations for two a.m.”

He didn’t say so, but I think he was getting as tight inside as I was. We were close—thirty hours from five thousand dollars—enough to go through college in good shape.

Saturday was a bell-ringer. By six o’clock in the evening we had parked over four thousand cars, and they were still coming. The safe was full of tens and twenties, all nicely wrapped and labeled, and our two suitcases were beside it. Still the money was pouring in. Nine cars a minute. One every seven seconds. Two hundred and fifty dollars an hour. It was better than a mint. The basement floor was beginning to fill up.

At six thirty Slim was bringing a car back to full size and saying to me, “Watch this one. This is the building inspector’s car; he’s trying to get a clue.”

At that exact moment a voice spoke behind us. “I beg your pardon, gentlemen.” It was one of those clear, soft voices with little tinkling bells in it. Know what I mean?

Slim turned and stared. “Madam,” he said, “don’t you know the sign says ‘No Admittance’?”

She looked repentant. “I’m sorry.” She looked hurt. “I didn’t think you gentlemen would mind.” She turned as if to go.

I saw Slim melting down. I didn’t blame him. That girl could have melted tungsten. Yes, I recognized her from her pictures in the society section—the mayor’s wife.

Slim was apologizing. “I beg your pardon, Madam. It’s quite all right. Your loveliness and radiant beauty just startled us. We—”

While Slim was laying it on thick, the building inspector’s car was expanding. Now it became considerably too big for the stall and split it like a stick of dynamite going off in a shoebox. It split it into a thousand pieces and then stood there, a passenger car seven feet tall.

The mayor’s wife gave a little scream of delight. Slim gave a horrified gasp. I tried to faint.

“Oh,” she said, “such a big car!”

Slim moaned. “Please, Madam, will you leave now?”

She looked hurt again. “Yes, but will you please put this package in my car?”

“I will,” said Slim, through tight jaws. “But—”

“Why, that looks just like the building inspector’s car,” she said, wide-eyed. “It’s his number, too.”

“Madam,” begged Slim, “you’re no dummy; please leave now and let us get on with our work.”

She walked upstairs dubiously. Slim was studying the enormous car with a hopeless look on his face. Orders for cars to be taken out were pouring down the chute.

“What are we going to do now? We can’t run that car into the other stall, because it’s too big. It will take all night to build another stall, and no doubt the inspector is waiting up there with a squad of cops, hoping something will happen. After all, we’re costing LaBombard a million bucks.” His eyes opened suddenly. “I’ll bet he sent the woman down here to spy on us.”

A car came down the ramp and went into the reducing stall, and Slim automatically set the dial.

The telephone rang, and I could hear the voice from where I stood. “The building inspector wants his car.”

“Coming right up,” Slim said.

Then he looked at me. I looked at him. “Get that safe open,” he jerked out. I dived for it.

I was spinning the combination when I heard the voices. The building inspector was riding the ramp down to the basement. Then I heard more voices and saw the bottom half of two cops and Richard LaBombard on the freight elevator.

Slim hissed to me. “Make it snappy!”

I was trying to, but I couldn’t get the thing open. Five thousand dollars in that safe and I couldn’t get it. I spun the dial frantically and started over.

But now the ramp was filled with people. The cops were getting off the elevator. I jumped up and ran over to where Steve was standing.

The building inspector was staring bug-eyed at his huge car. Somebody went around the stall and saw the six-inch car crawling out. Somebody else took hold of the stall and shook it. “Where’s my car? What’s going on?”

Well, a mob is a funny thing. In about half a minute there were eight hundred people in that basement, and all of them tearing apart the reducing stall.

Slim and I hesitated no longer. We ran up the stairway and sifted out through the crowd. …

At three o’clock in the morning Slim said to me, “You think that brakeman will kick us off?”

The brakeman came to us, sitting up there in the fresh night breeze on top of a carload of lettuce going east from California. He looked at me and then, as if he didn’t believe it, he held his lantern up and examined my head all the way around.

“Why don’t you go back to the farm? This ain’t no life for you,” he growled.

“I am considering that very seriously,” I said with as much dignity as I could.

Remember the 4th!

This was a warm day in August—a very warm day. Slim Coleman, my partner in detection work, says the sun is ninety million miles away, but this day it must have sneaked up pretty close. You could even see the heat waves coming up off the sidewalk. You can’t fry an egg on the pavement in Fort Worth, though, because you can’t stay out in the sun that long.

I mopped my brow, slung the water off my fingertips, and went into the lobby of the National Bank Building. The washed air made it cool and nice in there, and I slowed down to enjoy it. But one of the elevators came down, the door slid open, and the first man to get off was Swanberg, the building manager—our landlord—all dressed up in striped trousers and a fancy vest and wearing a high wing collar and a genuine cravat. He looked impeccable, immaculate—and cool.

I wheeled and marched back outside into the sun. Slim and I were three months behind with the rent, and I figured the only reason Swanberg hadn’t ordered us out was that he just hadn’t gotten around to it. I didn’t want to run into him. If we could have paid our rent I wouldn’t have been carrying ham sandwiches and a bottle of coffee in my coat-pockets up to Slim Coleman while he worked on the Brain-Finder.

The heat almost smothered me after the coolness of the lobby. Damn that guy Swanberg, anyway. He was always so perfect, so completely unaffected by the weather, so supercilious and so cold, so mechanical. You knew he’d never had any trouble and never would have, because he would never be swayed by anything but cold logic. It’s only we humans with sentiments who get in trouble.

It was his untouchableness that griped me. He was so inhumanly perfect he always made me feel rough and uncouth. You know how it is. If I could just get something on him to throw off that complex, I’d be happy even if we did have to vacate. I guess I spent my time daydreaming about Swanberg—Swanberg wearing an old-fashioned nightcap, Swanberg slurping his coffee, Swanberg sleeping with his socks on—anything human.

What wouldn’t I have given to have a picture of him in the roller coaster the way I had been the night of July the Fourth, with a perfectly strange, perfectly gorgeous, slim blonde throwing her arms around his neck the way that one had around mine. I was willing to bet he had a big, hefty wife at home who made him step.

I shivered whenever I thought about that blonde. She was the kind I would have liked to marry, only one like that was way out of my reach. I didn’t have much education and I didn’t always know what to do around a real high-class female. That’s why I had been riding the roller coaster alone.

Well, there was nothing for it now but the coal-chute. A truck was backed up to the sidewalk and two very black-faced men were pushing coal down a steel chute through a manhole in the sidewalk. I ducked into the alley, unrolled the bundle under my arm, and threw out a pair of khaki coveralls. I hated this, but I did it anyway; I had to. We couldn’t afford to have my suit cleaned every time I went in through the sidewalk, so I got into the coveralls and zipped them up. I watched around the corner. When the truckers raised the steel bed, I walked up to the open hole in the sidewalk and dropped in casually.

I’m a short man anyway, a little on the chunky side, and that coal-hole was like a furnace. The sweat poured down my back and chest and the coal-dust poured into my nostrils. I got out of there as fast as I could and took the freight elevator to the twenty-second floor. I went through the hall, unlocked the door, got inside, and locked it again.

“That you, Doc?” came Slim Coleman’s deep voice.

“Yeah.” I held the coveralls out of the window, slapped the coal-dust out of them, took off my damp suit-coat and laid it on top of the desk, got the electric iron out of the desk-drawer and plugged it in. Our sign said Coleman & Hambright, Private Investigators, and we had to maintain appearances, but I wished we could afford a store-bought pressing. I brushed my pants, but they were damp, too, so I took them off and laid them out on the desktop, over some papers, with the creases pinched tight. I mopped my brow and went into the other room.

Slim Coleman looked up from a workbench covered with wires, tubes, condensers, and all kinds of electrical gadgets. He had a soldering-iron poised above something that looked like a forty-eight-tube radio. He had deep, deep brown eyes that always looked through everybody, but Slim was a hundred-percent. In fact, it was his loyalty that had us behind the eight-ball now. If he had dissolved partnership instead of offering to pay the damages the time I fell from a second-story window and went through a skylight into a whole tableful of expensive orchids—but no, Slim paid it all—twenty-two hundred dollars before he got through, because the cold air ruined a lot more orchids. And I hadn’t even gotten the evidence I was after. (No, it was just happenstance that I fell from the bedroom window of a movie star.)

“What luck?” said Slim in his husky voice.

“I served them, but look, Slim, I hope you get that Brain-Finder going pretty quick. Not that I mind crawling under the length of three pullman cars and cutting my ankles on the cinders to serve divorce papers on Tom Ellingbery, who’s worth a million. Not that I mind doing all that for a measly five bucks, but when I have to come through the sidewalk in the summertime to duck the landlord—”

Coleman’s face lighted up. “The Brain-Finder is ready for a tryout,” he said. “Shall I show you yourself the night of July the Fourth?”

Well, partly because I guess I didn’t have much real faith in the gadget, I said “Okay,” and went to get the four ham sandwiches and the coffee in a milk-bottle out of my coat-pockets. That was why I couldn’t take off the coat when I put on the coveralls—for fear of spilling the coffee. Then I groaned and ran for the desk. There was a brown puddle spreading on the desk and soaking up my coat. I very nearly said “Damn!”

“I’ve got your brain wavelength,” Slim was saying. I started mopping up with my handkerchief while I hung the coat up to dry. “Now, all I have to do is—come here, Doc!”

I put the sandwiches on the bench in front of him, but for once Slim didn’t even reach. He looked at me and his deep-set eyes were burning. “We are going to be the greatest private investigators in history,” he said. “In fact, we’ll make history. Doc, we’ll be the most important men in America.”

I should have been more enthusiastic, but things were going so badly—“I don’t care,” I told him, “about being a great man, if I can just quit ducking the landlord. I want to walk in under his nose and not be scared of him. If you want to fill my cup to overflowing, just let me use that thing long enough to get something on him.”

Slim was already turning dials. Tubes were lighting up. The set was humming. Pretty soon he pointed to a screen, and I damn near lost my breath. There on a screen about twelve by eighteen inches, big enough so there wasn’t any mistake, I saw myself on the night of July Fourth, just as I bought one ticket for the roller coaster.

I guess my eyes stuck out a foot, for Slim was looking at me with that kind of sad smile. “Roller coasters,” he said gently. “Got enough, Doc?”

I gulped. “Plenty. Cut it off, please.” In the screen I saw the blonde just behind me, and I didn’t want Slim to see her put her arms around me when the roller coaster went over the dip.

Slim smiled and snapped a bunch of switches. The lights in the tubes went out. “Think what this will mean in criminal prosecutions, to be able to follow a man in the past. Present-day testimony will be archaic. The courts won’t have to take anybody’s word for anything; they can follow a man and watch him in the past.”

“Judge Monday wouldn’t admit that kind of evidence,” I pointed out.

“Naturally not. It will take twenty-five years to get this kind of evidence admitted in court. In the meantime, we’ll have to go easy. But we can make millions, just by bluffing. When we know that a man was playing poker in Jones’s basement until six o’clock Sunday morning, then we can bluff and put it over. Just so we don’t tangle with a real tough guy the first time. For instance—sh! Somebody’s at the door.”

Slim ran to the door while I ran for my pants. I ducked back into the other room and got them on. I heard the voice. It was a man’s voice, and I had heard it before—just recently. I peeked out. Yes, it was Tom Ellingbery. I stayed quiet.

“A potbellied little guy just served divorce papers on me,” he said harshly. “I got off the train and came here. A friend of mine sent me; I want your services.”

“Yes,” said Slim.

“Here’s a hundred-dollar bill,” Tom Ellingbery said. “Start shadowing my wife; get something on her. I’ll give you five thousand to get something—ten if it’s necessary,” he said with a slight leer.

Slim gravely picked up the C note. “We don’t do business that way,” he said; “but if your wife has been misbehaving we’ll find it out.”

Ellingbery was a big man with a sharp go-getter look about him. He stared hard at Slim and Slim stared back. Ellingbery’s expression didn’t show anything; then he left.

Slim locked the door after Ellingbery, and I took off my pants and set up the ironing-board on the desk. Slim went back to adjust the dials on his machine.

“This gadget is a sort of super-sensitive radar,” he said as it warmed up. “I can tune it to your brainwaves and pick you up anywhere within forty miles or three months.”

A purple indicator began to wink. “It proves I’ve got brains, anyway,” I pointed out.

“Yes, your waves come in at a frequency of approximately 1,832,956,000. That’s as close as I can tune it so far, but that’s plenty close enough. There are other characteristics, such as power and damping and height of crest and so on, that make it selective enough to pick out any one person in the United States if it could reach that far.”

“And then you can see everything I do?”

“No, I can see only what you see with your own eyes.”

Then I must have been staring at the blonde. I held my breath when I asked, “Can you tell what I’m thinking?”

“No.”

I breathed again.

“I can translate what you say into language, though. Something happens when I throw two hundred and twenty volts into this bank of tubes. As near as I can figure, it creates a ‘time-warp’—which doesn’t mean much of anything objectively. I don’t know how it works; I couldn’t even duplicate it. I suppose some high-powered electronics engineer could figure it out, but I don’t want anybody but you and me even to know about it. What I’m interested in is what we can do with it.”

“What I’m interested in,” I said, “is how much money we can make with it.”

Slim looked at me with his great burning eyes while the steam rose from under the iron on my pants.

“You’re about to find out.” The ground-glass screen slowly lighted. A new bank of tubes began to sparkle and then settled down into a greenish glow. Slim turned dials, and there was the figure of a woman on the screen.

“That,” said Slim, “is Mrs. Tom Ellingbery.”

Well, of course I couldn’t see her face. She was playing bridge, apparently. Her hands looked nice. The woman at her left said, “I hear you’ve filed suit against your husband.”

Mrs. Ellingbery reached for a king, but her fingers were nervous. She played a six instead and lost the trick. “Yes,” she said quietly, “I have.” Her voice was sad.

I waited a minute. Then, “How did you know how to tune in on her?” I asked Slim.

“I got her wave-characteristics when she came up the other day to get us to serve the papers,” he said. “I got Tom’s today while we were talking. The machine was all set and the recording needles made a permanent record.”

I swallowed. “Can you get the landlord’s characteristics too?”

Slim held up a sheet of ruled paper. “Got his already. I was just practicing; I got him when he was trying to hammer the door down yesterday.”

Suddenly I felt a deep peace. I had the landlord in my power, now, and I didn’t have to hurry; I could take my time.

But Slim notched me down. “Get this hundred changed,” he said. “Give the landlord fifty and then have the telephone connected again.”

I took the hundred.

“Get some more sandwiches, too. We’ll be here late tonight.”

Well, the landlord wasn’t as sarcastic as I had feared. He defrosted slightly when he saw the fifty. Now we owed him only two hundred. I knew he was probably going to put us out on September the first, but I soothed my hurt feelings by imagining him walking around in his shorts. There is nothing else that will so undignify a man. But before long—in fact, as soon as I could get to the Brain-Finder while Slim wasn’t watching—I’d get the facts.

We watched Mrs. Ellingbery for four straight nights and days. She went visiting; she played bridge; she shopped. She never did give more than a second glance at any man, and she didn’t talk to any man over the phone. We could see her only when she looked at herself in the mirror. That was enough.

We followed her like two bloodhounds, from the time she ate breakfast until she went to bed at night, but Slim turned the machine off when she sat down to remove her stockings. Slim always was a gentleman.

We went back in “time”—fast. Flashes here and there. But Mrs. Ellingbery was like Caesar’s wife. On the fifth day Slim called Tom Ellingbery and told him he was dropping the case, that his wife was above suspicion and it wasn’t worth while to watch her. I was glad, but Tom Ellingbery swore; anyway, he said he’d send a check for another hundred. Then Slim sat back and looked at me. “Now,” he said quietly, “we’ll turn this thing where it belongs.”

I’d been hoping he’d go out for a sandwich, now that we dared to use the passenger elevators, so that I could sneak a preview of the landlord biting his fingernails in seclusion, but no. Slim fixed his deep eyes on me and said, “We’ll see what Tom has been doing recently. Do you realize he hasn’t been in the picture but once in five days?”

Tom was it, all right. We trailed him that night to a big apartment house across town. Yes, it was a blonde, only this one had had considerable help from a bottle of peroxide. …

Slim made a deal with Mrs. Ellingbery’s lawyers. We were to get five triple-o’s if Mrs. Ellingbery won. So Slim spent the weekend trailing Tom for the past three months while I wrote it all down like a chronological history of the war. I was tickled over July the Fourth. On July the Fourth, Tom and the bleached blonde started out with a popcorn picnic and wound up—you guess. Riding the roller coaster! I could just imagine what old Judge Monday would say to that; that little scene would be worth half of the property settlement.

We were short on time. Some way or another Tom Ellingbery had rushed the trial, and it was set for August 30. We turned over our notes to Mrs. Ellingbery’s lawyers and sat back and waited. Private investigators never go near the courts unless they have to.

At four thirty that day the telephone rang. Slim listened, then he hung up. “Tom has got a couple of shrewd, tough lawyers,” he said. “We have to go to court. Tom isn’t admitting anything and he isn’t taking any bluffs. He demands proof.”

“Well,” I said, “for five M notes I’ll tell everything.”

Slim was worried. He talked to her lawyers, Youngquist and Rubicam, that night. The next morning we were both in court. It was direct examination. Slim identified himself, then he was asked: “You have investigated Tom Ellingbery’s activities over the past three months?”

“Yes.” Slim was very self-composed.

“Did you, on the night of August 26, observe him going into an apartment house at this address?”

“Yes.”

And so on—but never a word of where Slim was when he saw all this. Very clever, I thought, but when I looked at those sharp-eyed young fellows at Tom Ellingbery’s table, I knew it’d never get by.

Presently Mr. Youngquist said, “You may inquire.” I held my breath. But one of the young fellows looked up and said, “Are you going to put his partner on?”

“Yes,” said Mr. Youngquist.

“With that understanding, there are no questions of this witness, your honor.”

I jumped as if I had sat down on an electric griddle. It was plain even to me; they figured Slim was pretty sharp, so they’d wait for me, and in the meantime they wouldn’t tip me off by asking Slim any questions. I wished I could have held my breath for about three days.

I got along all right with Mr. Youngquist. I was careful not to say anything about where I had stood or sat or walked. I said, “Yes, I followed him,” because I did follow him with my eyes. Then Mr. Youngquist turned to the young fellow and said, “You may inquire.”

The young fellow got up slowly and looked at me easily and gently, but it was still August. I was sweating. I knew it was coming. I looked at Slim. Slim was sweating too. I looked at Mr. Youngquist. He wiped the perspiration from his forehead.

“You say,” the young fellow began softly, “that you and your partner followed Mr. Ellingbery from sometime in June?”

“Yes.”

“You testified, I believe, that on the night of July the Fourth, Tom Ellingbery and this girl were at the amusement park?”

“Yes.”

“And I believe you have cited some eight or nine dates up to the fifteenth of July.”

I looked at Mr. Youngquist and I was astonished to see his face the color of bleached muslin.

“Well, did you or did you not?”

I looked at Slim. He was puzzled, too. Finally I nodded.

“Will you say it for the record, please?”

“Yes.”

“That is to say, you are now testifying that you followed Mr. Ellingbery on each of eight or nine occasions prior to July 15, and each time with your partner at your side?”

“Yes.”

“And always at Mrs. Ellingbery’s request?”

“Yes.” That was a nasty question, but it had to be answered yes.

“Were you here in court yesterday?”

“No, sir.” I would have said, “No, your majesty,” if it would have helped.

“You didn’t hear Mrs. Ellingbery testify that her suspicions were first aroused when somebody reported to her that on July the Fourth Tom Ellingbery was riding the roller coaster with another girl?”

I wish I could have jumped into the Brain-Finder and gone back about two weeks. I would have walked through the sidewalk while the coal was being poured.

“No,” I said finally.

The young fellow looked triumphantly at Mr. Youngquist, who looked as if he would like to be buried in ashes up to his ears.

“That’s all.”

Mr. Youngquist rallied and put Slim back on the stand. Then there was a recess. Mr. Youngquist and Mr. Rubicam and Slim and Mrs. Ellingbery and I went into a big huddle out in the hall. “That’s what comes of messing around with imbecilic things like this Brain-Finder,” Mr. Youngquist moaned. “Why didn’t we stick to straight law?”

“Because we couldn’t win that way,” Mr. Rubicam reminded him. “We didn’t have any real evidence.”

Well, they decided the only chance to win the case was to have Slim tell about and demonstrate the Brain-Finder. Slim didn’t like to do that; but we needed those five G’s. That afternoon he told. The next morning we lugged it into court and set it on a table with the screen facing the judge.

There was a crowd in court that morning, thanks to a news story in the morning Herald. Slim groaned; crowds aren’t good for private investigators. I pricked up my ears when in marched Mr. Swanberg, our landlord, as austere as striped trousers could possibly make him, but with a beauteous blonde in a pink dress, clinging as if she was afraid he’d get away. That opened my eyes. Maybe the old iceberg was human after all, to rate that kind of devotion. Maybe he did have an occasional moment of abandonment when he would lick the butter from his knife. If we ever got through this mess I was going to find out. “That’s Mrs. Swanberg,” Youngquist said to Slim.

I looked his wife over in my best professional style. I thought I’d seen her some place, and a detective is supposed to remember faces, but I couldn’t quite place her. Anyway, there were now three blondes mixed in with that courtroom—and that’s a lot of blondes. Mr. and Mrs. Swanberg sat down at one side opposite the jury-box where they could see the screen of the Brain-Finder as well as the judge. I suppose Swanberg had read the story and wanted to see what we were up to in his building. Mrs. Ellingbery sat across the counsel table from me. She was a winner if there ever was one.

Slim went on the stand. He demonstrated the Brain-Finder very feebly—that is, innocuously. It was obvious that Youngquist was scared to death of what might happen.

And again Tom Ellingbery’s lawyers passed up cross examination of Slim. I knew they were waiting for me.

They were. “Do you understand this machine?” one asked me scornfully.

“No, sir.”

“You know how to work it, don’t you?”

“Yes. I think so.”

“Do you mean to tell this court that you can adjust the dials and gadgets on this thing and see what I was doing last week or the week before?”

I tried to be cautious. “If it’s plugged in.”

“Okay, we’ll plug it in.”

He invited me to step down and turn on the switches. I looked at Slim. He nodded. After all, there was nothing else to do. I went.

Some of the tubes crackled and then settled down to a steady green glow, and one bank showed purple. Then the lawyer said, “Now, do you mean to tell me you can tune this contraption in on a man’s brain and find him anywhere in the past?” He sounded completely skeptical.

“Within three months,” I said defiantly.

“For instance, you testified that Tom Ellingbery was riding the roller coaster on the night of July the Fourth with the girl who has been named in this case. You saw this on this screen?”

“Yes.”

“Can you tune it in again?”

Well, I knew this was all preliminary. It would take something absolutely dynamic to convince Judge Monday that the Brain-Finder was the real thing and not a fake. So I wasn’t worrying—yet. “Yes,” I said, and set the dials to Tom Ellingbery’s brainwaves. I picked up Tom and the bleached blonde just as they stepped into the roller-coaster car, and followed them around the ride. It wasn’t very sensational; she screamed and hid her eyes and grabbed Tom around the neck. Standard technique.

Then the lawyer said, “Can you pick up your own brainwave on this thing?”

“Yes.”

“What were you doing on the night of July the Fourth?”

“I was—” I swallowed. “I was riding the roller coaster.”

I think somebody snickered.

“Can you show us?”

“Yes,” I said cautiously.

I began to adjust the dials. Again the amusement park flickered over the ground glass, as seen through my eyes. I was in line. I put my money on the counter to buy a ticket. I saw a slim white hand reach up to the window from my left and I started to turn. Then it hit me!

That gorgeous blonde! That girl who had thrown her arms around me in the car a minute later. That was Swanberg’s wife.

I looked around at them in the courtroom. I knew what was happening on the screen. I hadn’t looked at her face until she got into the car after me. Mrs. Swanberg was leaning over, now, watching the screen. One arm was slipped through the landlord’s elbow and she was surreptitiously but affectionately patting the back of his hand. Swanberg himself looked completely blissful. What had she been out there alone for, that night? Well, no telling. Maybe he’d been out of town and she’d felt like doing something childish. Certainly there was no meanness or deceit in her face. She was in love with him. And he, in spite of all his austerity, was obviously in love with her.

I looked out the window. There was no doubt that the fame of the Brain-Finder by now would be all over town. Within a week we’d be flooded with work—high-priced work. We’d take only the very best cases, the highest priced, the least messy. We’d pay the rent. We’d eat in restaurants instead of carrying sandwiches. In another three months we’d be rolling in money—and almost without work. If we wanted to work hard with the Brain-Finder, we’d make millions. I could maybe find myself the right kind of girl to marry.

I looked back at the screen. I had just settled myself in the seat of the roller-coaster car. A pink dress came into my field of vision on the right. Yes, sir, this demonstration would do it. This, and those to follow. Whatever Judge Monday might say, there would be an appeal, and we’d have to take the thing to the Supreme Court, and how could any judge ignore it if Slim could show the judge himself working on his pet corn the night before? We were about to be what is vulgarly but happily known as “in the bucks.”

What would happen to Swanberg? I remembered how I’d always pictured his wife as unattractive, and all of a sudden it made me feel kind of ashamed. He had certainly shown good taste in his choice of a wife.

Well, pretty quick now I could afford to travel in that kind of company.

I wondered what would happen when Swanberg saw his wife throwing her arms around me on the roller coaster. I guessed maybe he wouldn’t be cold; he’d be jealous. Well, a man with a young and beautiful wife—somehow it kind of got me. I mean that sort of calf-like happiness. He loved her and he felt secure in the knowledge that she loved him, and—well, you know how it is.

Gosh, how I wanted that money. Here it was within our reach—the thing we’d worked so hard for, the reason I’d crawled under pullman cars and gone through the sidewalk and sneaked in to evade the landlord—all so Slim could keep working on the Brain-Finder. He had it now. Slim didn’t know how to duplicate it, but one was all we needed. That one was worth a fortune.

I looked back at the Swanbergs, sitting there so close together. Swanberg hadn’t really been tough with us. In fact, he’d been lenient. Three months was a lot to be behind. No, I guess the only thing I hadn’t really liked about him was the fact that he was always so perfectly dressed and so cool while I had to go through the sidewalk on a hot day in August and then press the sweat out of my clothes with a flatiron.

I looked at the girl. She was nice. She hadn’t been doing anything out of the way that night. She certainly hadn’t made any sort of pass at me. And they were in love.

I guess I had no business being an investigator. I looked at the judge, watching every move with his sharp old eyes. I glanced at Slim Coleman, sitting there, looking a little puzzled, his eyes deep and burning. I tried to ask Slim to forgive me. I looked at the screen. The roller-coaster car was pulling up to the top of the first hump.

I took hold of the Brain-Finder. It was heavy, but I picked it up and held it over my head, then I heaved it onto the floor, and it was nothing but a mass of loose wires and broken glass.

A woman screamed. Youngquist fainted. Slim came running with a question in his deep eyes. Tom Ellingbery’s lawyer was triumphant. The judge pounded for order. …

This is four days later. Tom Ellingbery and his wife made up. Last night’s paper showed them on the roller coaster. He was quoted as saying: “All I wanted was to ride the roller coaster.” And she had said: “Boys will be boys.”

Slim brings me four ham sandwiches and coffee twice a day. He got acquainted with the blonde that Tom Ellingbery was riding the roller coasters with, and they went out to the park and had five dollars worth of rides the night that Tom Ellingbery paid Slim the five G’s. (Tom said it was worth that much to have his wife back.) And do you know whom Slim and the blonde ran into at the Park? Mr. and Mrs. Swanberg. First thing I ever heard of a man in a tailcoat riding the roller coaster.

In fact, everybody’s got a blonde but me, and everybody’s riding the roller coaster but me. I’m not riding them now. I got thirty days for contempt of court.

The Mischievous Typesetter

The judge reared back. High-Pockets waited. “In my opinion,” his honor began a little ambiguously, “a linotype operator is very near the bottom of the scale of humanity. There is only one person who stands beneath him. That is the poet.” The judge’s eyes turned full on High-Pockets, all seven gangling feet of him. “You,” the judge said ominously, “are both.”

High-Pockets waited in dread. He had a premonition that this wasn’t even going to be a nice jail sentence where he could meditate and reflect on his strange power over linotypes. This was going to be the workhouse. The situation was desperate indeed.

“You profess to be a barnstormer and a student of mechanical nature.” The judge smiled sarcastically. “I can offer you an unusual opportunity for research. As an old proofreader, I occasionally help out on the Daily News, and it has come to my attention that there is a linotype on the News known as No. 7 that recently has begun to misbehave. Without apparent reason, it has become almost useless.”

High-Pockets cringed with the impact of the knowledge that His Honor had once been a proofreader. The traditional enmity between proofreaders and operators, High-Pockets perceived, was about to be judicially resolved. So he cringed. He was very sad.

“Suppose you go up there and try your wizardry on No. 7.” His Honor suggested. “In the meantime, thirty days suspended sentence. If you’re back here before your time is up, it will be sixty days. And if there is drunkenness connected with it,” he said, looking disdainfully at High-Pockets’ red nose, “it will be ninety. Is that clear?”

“Yes, your honor.” High-Pockets mumbled, but he was thinking of other things. He had been sentenced to work at his trade. That meant contact with proofreaders, and High-Pockets bristled. But the bristling subsided rapidly, as High-Pockets, simulating a grateful smile from long habit, realized with a sickly feeling that for perhaps the first time in his long career, a proofreader had had the complete and final word, and High-Pockets did not dare to answer back. …

They spotted High-Pockets coming across the composing-room of the Daily News when they saw a red nose following an eccentric orbit up among the fluorescent lights. High-Pockets didn’t exactly duck the lights. When he came face to face with one, his incredibly tall knees limbered up and he sort of weaved under it.

The union chairman met him with a handshake. “High-Pockets Jones,” he said, grinning, “Dean of Barnstormers and Wizard of the Linotype. I know you from your picture. Can you really make a linotype stand up on its hind legs and talk?”

“Well,” High-Pockets said in a modest, booming voice, “I will admit that’s one of my more difficult stunts.”

The chairman guffawed, and they steered High-Pockets to the slip-board. “I can put you on a week’s stretch.”

High-Pockets stopped as if he had walked into a brick wall. “No!” he boomed. “Can’t do it! Haven’t worked five days straight in twenty years.”

“But look, High-Pockets. Look at it this way. You’re an old-time barnstormer, aren’t you?”

High-Pockets winced.

“Well,” the chairman said diplomatically, “there’s not as much call for barnstormers as there used to be, but—” he said it quickly—“here’s a new field. It needs a good barnstormer as much as they ever did.”

High-Pockets listened intently.

“This poor guy has to sit on No. 7. That’s the linotype nobody can do anything with. The poor devil had to lay off because she pretty nearly drove him crazy. Now you are the guy who can make a linotype behave.” His voice was persuasive. “Won’t you help this guy out for a few nights?”

For twenty years it had been High-Pockets’ unbroken rule not to hire out for more than a day at a time. “Short-term contracts,” he insisted. But now—well, the world was changed. Maybe this was to be the future of barnstorming—taming machines instead of foremen. If so, it meant he still had a place in the world. And to fulfill that destiny he would even accept a whole week’s work. He took off his rain-wrinkled coat with a sigh.

He was waiting for time to be called when Arturius Wickware, the linotype machinist on the News, came up to him with short, mincing steps and a scowl that undoubtedly was a habit. “Are you the guy that has such wonderful control over a linotype?” he demanded. He wouldn’t give High-Pockets the satisfaction of looking up at him. He scowled at High-Pockets’ breastbone.

High-Pockets was solemn as he stared over Arturius’ head. “I get along well with them.” He smiled gently then. “Somehow a linotype always does what I want it to do.” He looked down and saw the crowd around him and decided he owed them an explanation. “My theory is that any piece of machinery is electrified by some force that I call personal electricity. I don’t exactly know what that is but it seems to bind the piece of machinery as a whole. I think maybe it’s a negative charge, and I think most men are charged positively with that same force, so that men get along well with machines. Opposite poles attract, you know.”

Arturius Wickware sputtered, but now High-Pockets had to go on. “Sometimes a man comes along who happens to be negatively charged, and he can’t handle a piece of machinery at all. But now I—you see this scar in the middle of my forehead—” he removed his faded hat, “I was struck by lightning on a freight train out in Utah, and I think it multiplied my ‘personal’ electricity potential a lot—maybe millions of times—so machinery just has to do what I want it to, because it wants to do it. You see?”

There was an odd silence; then the chairman spoke. “Old No. 7 started acting up when they built the first uranium pile south of town here, but it really went bad when it was hit by lightning that followed down the ventilation pipe two months ago.”

High-Pockets’ blue eyes opened wide. “Maybe its negative field was reversed by some stray rays from the pile, and then when the lightning hit it, it intensified the field so that the machine is now strongly positive. You know how it is,” he said earnestly. “A body illuminated by ultraviolet light becomes positively charged, and even a hot body becomes positively charged by what they call thermionic emission. Well, that’s okay. A linotype is exactly like a woman. It has a soul—if you know how to reach it.”

Old Arturius snorted so loudly the electric relay on No. 7 made contact and the heating switch came on with a clatter. “You can work on No. 7 tonight,” he said acidly. “Let’s see if it’s got a soul.” He turned on his heel and stamped back to his bench. …

It never occurred to High-Pockets to doubt his success with No. 7. He carefully hung his ten-year-old coat in an empty locker and made sure the pint of bourbon was safely in the inside pocket of the coat. Then he walked into the composing-room and over to No. 7, and stood for a moment looking her over. He frowned. “It’s almost as if she was laying her ears back and getting ready to snarl at me,” he said wonderingly.

“She’ll snarl,” said Arturius at his back. “She’ll bite, before the night’s over.”

High-Pockets tried to look amused. “I’ll have her setting type by herself before lunch time,” he promised.

High-Pockets got the lowest chair in the composing-room, to bring his arms down near the keyboard. His nose was still red and he weaved a little in the chair, but he began to fold in his arms until his hands were over the keyboard.

The first take went smoothly. High-Pockets could feel a clash of wills, but he was slow and careful. He set two more takes, and nothing happened, so he began to relax. His third take was a short piece of telegraph copy for the second edition. He put it in the copy holder and then decided to get a drink of water. He ran into some friends and they spent five minutes around the fountain before the foreman came by.

High-Pockets went back to the machine. He sat down and got his arms tucked in, then reached for a slug with his name on it and started to put it in the stick. Then he frowned and rang the bell for the machinist.

“Somebody’s playing tricks on me,” he said. “Who’s been working here?”

“Nobody but you,” Arturius said nastily.

High-Pockets licked his lips. “I’d swear I didn’t set this take.” But Arturius looked intensely satisfied and went away. Thoughtfully High-Pockets took the type out of the stick and put his take slug on it and went to the dump. When he sat down again he shook his head and rubbed his eyes before he went to work. “No. 7 musta set that take herself,” he muttered, “but that’s not according to union rules.” He said it without actually believing it.

He got along all right until nearly lunch time. By then, he was dry again, and he got a long take of the next day’s editorial and stuck it in the copy board, then went to the fountain, and finally decided to go to the washroom and smoke a cigarette.

When he got back to the machine he picked up a take slug and pulled back the slug-stacker—and then he froze tight.

High-Pockets looked a little scared. He licked his lips and took the stick out of the machine. It was a long take, about ten inches of type. He laid it across his knees and compared it with the copy. It checked. He read it over upside down. Not a single error.

“Well, I didn’t set it, anyway,” he muttered. “I couldn’t possibly set an okay proof, the way I feel.”

Somewhat resignedly he took the type to the dump.

The dump-man looked at him. “Turning ’em out pretty fast. Whatta you think this is, a piecework town?”

High-Pockets looked chastened, but said nothing.

He went to the copy desk. There was nothing now but want ads. He got a take and then he had a bright idea. He put the want ads on the copy board and went for a drink of water. He was dry again, anyway. He took plenty of time, and then came back and confidently picked up a take slug.

But he got a jolt when he looked at the stick. It was empty.

High-Pockets nodded wisely. “So it doesn’t like want ads any better than anybody else,” he said to himself. “Now, that’s a dirty shame.”

He got all folded in and started to operate. But at the first letter he touched, the keyboard belt broke. He called Arturius and had it fixed, and tried again. The mats jammed up in the chute.

He cleaned them out and then started carefully hitting one letter at a time. But the very first one came to the star wheel, and rang the bell again. “Star wheel spring is loose,” he said. “She won’t bring the mats down.”

Arturius looked at him with a scowl that bore the heavy responsibility of the entire world, and then without a word sat down to fix it. He stood by while High-Pockets tried again. The line finally was filled and High-Pockets sent it in and started on the second line.

“Wait a minute,” said Arturius. “You didn’t get a slug.” He opened the vise. “Short-line stop is out of adjustment,” he growled. “What’s the matter with this machine, anyway?”

High-Pockets looked worried. “Maybe she don’t like want ads,” he said. “Maybe I better set this take somewhere else.”

Arturius grunted. High-Pockets went to No. 8. He set the want ads with one eye on No. 7. He was quite sober now.

The copy-cutter wasn’t looking when High-Pockets got back to the desk, and High-Pockets did something he’d never done before in his life. He “worked the hook”—instead of taking want ads, he very quietly took a piece of minion, and then looked around guiltily to see if anybody noticed.

He wound his way back to No. 7 and got all set. Arturius was gone. High-Pockets by now realized that he was up against worthy opposition. If he had reached No. 7’s soul, he had stirred it the wrong way. From now on he would be extremely careful.

Things went all right until after the cast. The line went up to transfer—and there it stuck. High-Pockets sighed and rang the bell. Arturius came, but the scowl on his face was diluted with self-satisfaction.

He started to lock the spaceband lever, but when he touched the latch, the spaceband lever went over with a crash and the line of mats spilled out in the intermediate channel.

High-Pockets sighed noisily and got up. Arturius was using some uncomplimentary language, and the gleam of satisfaction was all in High-Pockets’ eyes now.

They picked up the mats, and Arturius pulled out the clutch lever to let the machine finish its revolution. But it stuck on ejection. The clutch grabbed and chattered. He threw the clutch lever in and went around behind. He backed the machine by hand and hammered with the ejector lever. The slug wouldn’t come out.

He came back, looked at the knife, looked at the ejector blade, examined the mouthpiece. “This mill is nuts,” he said in his sourest tone, and added some explanatory remarks that verged on redundancy. He held up the ejector lug while High-Pockets pulled the clutch lever and let the machine go on over.

Arturius had to loosen the mold-cap to get the slug out. Then he stood back for High-Pockets to sit down. But by this time High-Pockets had awakened. He looked hard at the copy and whispered to himself, “Oh-oh, no wonder. We’ve got society. Don’t blame her.” He told Arturius he had to get a drink. When he came back, Arturius was gone, and very quietly High-Pockets went over to No. 8 and set the type.

His next take was a nice piece of telegraph on green copy paper. “She ought to like this.” High-Pockets thought, but his face had a wondering look.

He put the copy in the holder and got ready to massage the keyboard. But he’d just got his arms folded up and his fingers stretched out when the mats began to drop into the assembling elevator. They dropped with perfect timing. The assembling elevator filled and High-Pockets’ eyes began to gleam. “She’ll have to wait for me to send the line in,” he thought. But old No. 7 wouldn’t be denied. The elevator went up, the line went in, the elevator came down, and mats started dropping again. High-Pockets got up and went to a window. He leaned out and breathed the crisp night air.

When he got back the take was finished.

He got the second take of the same story and went back to the machine. He put the take in the copy holder and then, out of habit, he looked at the stick. It was already half full of type. He was almost afraid to compare it with his copy, but he did.

After he checked it, he got up and went to the locker room. Nobody else was there. He pulled the pint bottle out of his coal pocket and without hesitation violated another strict office rule—he took a good, long, healthy drink of bourbon.

He wiped his lips and came back. No. 7 was still running over. He looked at the type. There was a guideline that said “Third Add—Nazi Werewolves.” High-Pockets turned on his heel and went back to the locker room. This time he had two drinks, and when he finished he weaved a little more.

“Monkeying with souls,” he muttered, “is dangerous business.”

He was thankful the story had only three takes. First he thought he would dump the third take in the metal pot, but when he picked it up it was so hot that even he, with calloused fingertips from handling hot slugs for twenty years, couldn’t hold it. So he dumped both takes and turned off the motor, then went to lunch.

That is, he borrowed a dollar from the chairman and started for the restaurant. But he passed a saloon on the way, and decided he was more in need of a drink.

When he got back he had a little trouble with the fluorescent lights. They weaved when he weaved, and it took some rather delicate navigation to beat them to the punch. It was fortunate that the light tubes were fixed securely in their sockets, and fortunate that the foreman had gone into the office to check the time cards.

When High-Pockets got back to the copy desk, he was pretty fuzzy around the edges. He looked over his first take as soon as he got behind the desk. Then he gave a relieved sigh. This was Editorial. No. 7 wouldn’t be so fussy—he hoped.

He got four paragraphs through before he ran into trouble. Then some mats jammed up at the top of the assembler entrance cover. High-Pockets started to ring the bell, but decided not to. He could dig it out himself. He’d had enough trouble with Arturius for one night.

He opened the entrance cover, and a hundred mats fell down over his arm and onto the keyboard with an ominous tinkle. Their weight depressed some twenty keys, and the power drive immediately began to function, and the mats from those twenty channels dropped in twenty curving streams on the keyboard, which depressed still more keys and made more mats drop, and in about two minutes No. 7 had poured fifteen hundred mats into High-Pockets’ lap.

He did one thing before he rang the bell. He brushed the mats off the copy holder and looked at the rest of the paragraph. It ended, “—and the blame for Pearl Harbor thus lay at the door of the White House.”

High-Pockets got up, shedding mats by the hundreds. Arturius came, looking as if he were about to detonate. Half the operators in the shop were there to enjoy the fact that at least there was one man who wasn’t afraid to have trouble with No. 7.

Somebody chuckled and said. “Get a basket,” but High-Pockets knew it wasn’t meant for him and nobly disdained a reply. He was muttering to himself, “I’ve heard these machines called a lot of things in my time, but this is the first one I ever saw that could justifiably be called a Republican.”

The machinist was verbose, a little on the vicariously obscene side. High-Pockets helped him pick the mats off the floor, but it was almost an hour before they got the machine going again.

When they did, High-Pockets went back to look at the slip-board. He studied it for a few minutes with a queer look on his face, then started for the chairman. But halfway there, he changed his mind. No machine had ever got the best of him before, and he’d been up against some tough ones. He was a barnstormer, wasn’t he?

So he went back to the battle. But now there wasn’t any copy, so he wandered around with that queer look on his face, and finally wound up in the locker room where he decided he might as well kill the pint. He smoked a cigarette and stuck his head out of the window into the fresh air.

When the pint was thoroughly defunct he returned. The machine was quiet again, but the stick was half full. He didn’t even look at it. There wasn’t any copy, but he took the type to the dump.

The next take was copy for “Good Morning, Glory,” the paper’s star columnist. That seemed to go very well. No. 7 perhaps couldn’t quite make out what was happening. Well, that was nothing. Most columnists were like that.

Then again there wasn’t any copy. A young fellow came down from the newsroom and spoke to the copy-cutter. “There’ll be a story down for the eleven-fifteen edition,” he said. “ ‘Two Women Murdered.’ About a column.”

The copy-cutter looked at the clock. “It’s eleven o’clock now,” he said. “Where is it?”

“Just starting to write it upstairs. We’ll get it down as fast as we can.”

The copy-cutter grumbled. “Better have a makeover, then. We won’t have time to handle it.”

But High-Pockets knew better. He poked his head over the desk and sneaked a look at No. 7. She was grinding away. High-Pockets went back to the dump and looked at the guideline of his stickful without copy. It said, “Two Women Murdered.”

But nobody would ever give out a long take like that so near closing time. He looked again. He should have known. The half-a-stickful was divided into thirds, carefully guided “First Add” and “Second Add,” and at the bottom of the last add was a turned slug and a line, “More to Come.”

The copy tube swished, and a carrier thumped in the box. “Here,” the copy-cutter said, “here’s a precede on that atomic bomb explosion. You might as well set that while we’re waiting.”

“Okay,” said High-Pockets, and in the now hazy recesses of his mind he made a mighty resolution: he would set this take himself; No. 7 be damned.

He went straight to the machine. Mats were dropping, but High-Pockets just raised his eyebrows and reached up and turned off the power. That would stop her.

He got his copy all fixed and his arms folded in, and then he unfolded one arm and turned on the power while his right hand hovered over the keyboard. Apparently No. 7 didn’t quite know what to make of this new attack, and he was able to get several lines through before she figured it out. Then she seemed to sit back and get her breath, and High-Pockets, with a wide grin on his face, manipulated the keyboard fast enough to keep the machine hung so she wouldn’t get a chance on her own hook.

But eventually he had a pileup of mats and had to miss a line. He was crestfallen. But strangely enough, she didn’t start in when he got the assembling elevator clear. He watched her out of the corner of his eye while he gingerly assembled the line, but nothing happened. He sent that line in and watched it go through without any disturbance, then he sat back a moment and he and the machine sized each other up. Still no mats dropped of their own volition. High-Pockets grinned. Maybe he was beginning to sober up.

He set a line and sent it in, watching. It justified and the pot came forward to cast. “Hmp,” said High-Pockets. “Who said she’s human? Subhuman, I call it.”

Something happened when he said that. The second justification lever went up with a bang that shook the whole machine, and High-Pockets reached for the clutch lever with his left hand.

But he was so long he had to grab something with his right hand to balance, and just then the line delivery came back with a snap and smashed his right thumb.

“Ouch!” said High-Pockets, and jumped up and then he swore and shook his hand.

A minute later he sat down again with a determined gleam in his eyes. He tightened the vise-locking screws and leaned over to look at the line, down in the jaws, to be sure the mats were in alignment before he pulled the clutch. And just then the right hand locking stud came loose with a snap and spun clockwise, and the cross-handle cracked him on the chin.

High-Pockets took it like a man. He didn’t even swear this time. He got out of his chair. “I will see if that line is all right,” he muttered. “If I don’t—”

He tightened the screw, then he got his head in under the intermediate bar to look. And at that moment a gust of air blew a cloud of graphite out of the intermediate channel and filled his right eye. He was nearly blinded, but he didn’t ask for help. Very quietly he wound his way to the washroom. He cleaned his face and worked the graphite out of his eye as well as he could, and then, with a determined look on his face, went back.

Arturius reached the machine about the same time he did, “What did you leave her on the cast for?” he barked.

High-Pockets didn’t answer.

Arturius indulged in some choice blasphemy with its direction divided equally between High-Pockets and No. 7. High-Pockets felt sorry for Arturius. He went to the locker room and determined to his satisfaction that the pint was still dead, then he came back. The boy had left some proofs on his machine. High-Pockets picked them up to scan them. Then he swore vigorously. “Proofreaders!” he sputtered. “Comma chasers! Look at this!” he invited the world. “Put a hyphen in the word ‘good-will.’ Marked a double e in ‘employe.’ Changed ‘thous‑and’ to ‘thou‑sand!’ ” He clenched his fists and raised them far above his head. “Give me strength!” he groaned. “Give me strength! On top of everything else, the proofreaders have to go nuts too.”

He started for the proof room, clutching the proofs in one hand. His long arms swung as he weaved among the lights. He went in the door of the proof room and stood there a moment. His head was above the lights and for a moment he couldn’t see very clearly, but he demanded in his booming voice: “Who signed these proofs ‘R. M. S.’?”

There was a stir in the proofroom, and then a man at the far end of the table got to his feet. “I did,” he said in thunderous voice.

High-Pockets didn’t back down. “What the hell do you think this is—1910?” he demanded, waving the proofs. “This is a newspaper, isn’t it, not a dictionary?”

“Is it indeed?” said the man ominously, and High-Pockets thought he had heard that voice before. He stared toward the man and his eyes began to focus and then he saw who it was. A gulp started in High-Pockets’ adam’s-apple and traveled visibly down the full length of his body to the floor. He opened his mouth but no sound came out. His eyes became glazed like those of a man walking in his sleep.

“Your honor,” he said, at last, struggling to force words from his larynx and looking like a man in a very blue funk, “there are extenuating circumstances.”

Then he seemed to awaken. He looked around him. Through the glass windows of the proof room he saw a makeup man pushing a turtle to the stereotype room, and this seemed to give him a little grip on reality. He turned back with a certain air of assurance, as if he was about to take things decisively into his own hands. But he looked into His Honor’s stern countenance and that assurance wilted visibly. High-Pockets retreated in confusion.

Maybe No. 7 sympathized with him. At least she allowed him to correct the proofs without any trouble. High-Pockets even began to feel that there was some feeling of friendliness flowing between them.

He was working on his next take when he felt a presence behind him. He revolved in his chair, and he very nearly fell over when he once again faced His Honor, the Judge. His Honor had a long piece of pasted copy in one hand and was waving a proof in the other. “So,” His Honor said malevolently, “you’re the poet.”

“What are you talking about?”

“This.” His Honor waved the proof under High-Pockets’ nose. “You set this verse. It isn’t in the copy at all.”

High-Pockets felt uneasy. “Let’s see.” He read aloud:

“ ’Tis dawn in the woods. A gentleman slumbers
Beneath the protection of wild cucumbers.
The woodpeckers woodpeck, the rattlesnakes rattle,
And all the cockroaches prepare to do battle.”

High-Pockets gulped. He handed the proof back to His Honor: he revolved again and folded himself into the chair. He started to set type. Then he remembered. “Your Honor,” he said, “I had nothing to do with it. No. 7 did it.”

His Honor, goaded by High-Pockets’ temporary amnesia which looked very much like disrespect, exploded. “A machine! A machine did this?”

High-Pockets sent in the line and started another.

“Are you imputing intelligence to a machine?” His Honor demanded, and No. 7 seemed to hesitate for an instant. “No machine on earth could compose such awful poetry as this,” His Honor thundered.

No. 7 was casting. For no reason at all the plunger stuck in the bottom of the well and No. 7’s clutch chattered and shook the entire machine before High-Pockets shut off the power. High-Pockets revolved and looked at the judge and raised his eyebrows, then rang the bell.

This time the machinist was entirely speechless. High-Pockets pointed to the plunger. Arturius worked on it but couldn’t get it loose. He got a Crescent wrench. “Get hold of the first-elevator cam,” he said, “and back her up while I twist the plunger.”

His Honor stood by, waiting to take up the battle with High-Pockets.

High-Pockets got hold of the cam with a sardonic set to his lips. He yanked hard. No. 7 would find out who was boss.

But when he pulled, the screw holding the end of the second elevator starting spring came loose and the spring shot the screw into High-Pockets’ ribs with the force of a bullet. High-Pockets merely grunted.

“Wait, I’ll take the drive clutch,” Arturius said, as if he was beginning to be concerned.

High-Pockets shut off the power, and Arturius took hold of the clutch, one hand on each end, and turned forward.

The plunger started to lift. It came halfway up, and then the machine suddenly rolled backward again, with the heavy plunger spring helping it. The clutch spun like a top.

Arturius backed away holding the fingers of one hand.

“Get hurt?”

Arturius bit his lip. “No,” he said, “but pull that plunger pin before I try it again.”

High-Pockets pulled the pin, and Arturius got No. 7 off the cast. Then he went around to the front, took the controlling lever, and started to pull it out to finish the machine’s revolution.

He saw a loose mat on the vise and reached for it with his left hand. At that instant his hand slipped off the controlling lever, and the first elevator head came down with a crash.

But Arturius’ fingers were not there. He backed off and did the most thoroughly human thing he’d done in years. He thumbed his nose at No. 7. The judge looked skeptical.

“Look out!” High-Pockets yelled. “She’s backing!”

His long arms moved with astonishing speed. He practically snatched the judge up from the place where he stood and set him down again two feet away. And just in time, for a stream of silvery, molten metal rose in a wide arc from the vise-jaws of No. 7 and came down exactly where His Honor’s bald head had been. About three pounds of it descended to the floor and lay there hardening and smoking like an overdone pancake.

Sweat popped out on the judge’s bald head. His Honor’s eyes were bulging. “She squirted hot lead at me!” he said accusingly. “Maliciously and with malice aforethought.” He pulled out a handkerchief to wipe his bald head. His hands were steady. “If that lead had fallen on me,” he said plaintively, “it would have baked my skull. Why did she try to do that to me?”

“You made fun of her poetry,” High-Pockets pointed out. With a certain amount of pleasure he reflected that His Honor could hardly allege contempt, under the circumstances.

But his honor looked at High-Pockets with a new light in his eyes. “You may have saved my life,” he said thoughtfully.

Arturius Wickware looked desperate. “It can’t squirt,” he said. “The plunger pin isn’t in.”

High-Pockets pointed to the metal on the floor. “It did,” he said.

Arturius looked at No. 7 dourly and shut off the motor. “Please take No. 8,” he begged High-Pockets. It was the first time he had said “please” in thirty years.

High-Pockets was staring at the proof like a man in a trance.

Suddenly he made half a dozen long strides to the machinist’s bench. He laid hands on a twelve-pound sledgehammer. He came back with it over his shoulder, and before the horrified Arturius could utter a word, High-Pockets had gone to the rear of No. 7 and swung the sledge in one devastating left-handed blow that sheared through the ninth and tenth cams. Then he stepped to the right and crashed the hammer down on the pot-pump cam.

He stepped back, breathing hard, the hammer over his shoulder. Pieces of cast iron tinkled to the floor. “Well,” boomed High-Pockets, “I guess I fixed it, didn’t I?”

There was no answer. High-Pockets looked around. Arturius had quietly fainted. The judge looked horrified.

They revived Arturius by the simple expedient of putting a screwdriver in his big hand. He opened his eyes and stared at High-Pockets and shook his head slowly, incredulously.

High-Pockets helped him up. “Don’t worry,” he said.

Arturius sputtered and almost detonated. “Don’t worry!” he snorted. “Five hundred dollars worth of cams busted up and he says, ‘Don’t worry!’ ”

“It won’t cost that much,” said High-Pockets. “I’ll help you piece the cams together. You can get them welded.”

“No,” said Arturius. “I’ll get new ones.”

“It won’t work,” said High-Pockets.

“What won’t work?”

“I did that to chastise the machine. If it wants to be so independent, it will have to endure the penalties as well as enjoy the privileges. If you put in new cams, it will think it’s smart and go right ahead raising hell. But if you have the old ones welded and put back in, the welds, like scars, will remind No. 7 that she’s supposed to be a lady. As long as they are there, No. 7 will behave. I guarantee it.”

The judge wiped his bald head again. “I do believe you’ve got something there, Mr. Jones. If a machine assumes the right of self-determination, what would be more natural than to treat it as you would treat any other self-determining creature?”

High-Pockets heaved a tremendous sigh of relief. He saw now that his stay in the city would not be terminated as a guest in the workhouse. High-Pockets was very happy indeed.

“How can you be sure?” Arturius demanded.

“I’ll show you,” said High-Pockets. “Turn on the motor.”

Arturius did. A strange thing happened. No. 7 began to turn. She pulled herself off of the cast. Somehow she broke loose the hardened metal on her vise-jaws. It dropped to the floor in one big piece. She came to a normal stop and stood there obediently.

“That’s utterly impossible!” Arturius shouted. “It can’t even turn over—with those cams broken out.”

“She’s chastened,” High-Pockets said gently. “All you have to do from now on is to be firm.”

The judge came closer. “Mr. Jones,” he said, “I am beginning to believe that even a linotype operator has a place in this modern world. Suppose we all three go out and have a drink.”

High-Pockets turned off the motor. “I heard you the first time, Your Honor, and I am happy to report that there are no extenuating circumstances. Shall we go?”